Guide to the History of Computer Game Design Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
History of computer game design records
2001-2004
SC0717
Lowood, Henry
3 Linear feet
Papers from a Stanford University class on computer game design taught by Henry Lowood (STS 145).
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Copyright held by student authors; no photocopying is permitted.
Description of the Collection
Papers from a Stanford University class on computer game design taught by Henry Lowood (STS 145).
Access Terms
Computer games--Design.; Computer games--History.; Computer games--Programming.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - Spring 2001 Assignment 1 Game Reviews
    - Winter 2001 Game Paper Archives, 1 optical disc (CD-ROM) (Box 1)
    - Agnich, Michael - Sojourn (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Albert, Eric – SimCity Classic: History and Review (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Barnett, Joseph – Mega Man II (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Barrett, Ryan – Supspace Review (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brown, Todd – Super Mario Kart (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bruner, Christopher – Chrono Trigger review (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chan, Eric – Marathon: Game Review (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chang, Michael – Street Fighter II: The Original Warrior (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chao, Clifford – Game Review: Tekken 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chopra, Niti – The Legend of Zelda (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chu, Patricia (Sha Sha) – Review: King's Quest: Quest for the Crown (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Cretan, Aram – Wolfenstein 3D: the first game that ever made my pulse race (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dorie, Tony – Super Mario Bros. 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Driscoll, Adam - Marathon (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Fan, James – Chrono Trigger (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Fang, Nicholas – Game Review: Betrayal at Krondor (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hu, Yu Ping – Game Review: Wipeout (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Huang, Po-Wen Joseph – Review of Lemmings (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Jiricek, Aaron – Diablo: A Game Review (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Kochenderfer, Mykel – Sierra Online's Conquest of the Longbow: The Legend of Robin Hood (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Kolich, Thomas – Review of Street Fighter II Turbo: Hyper Fighting (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Kuo, Andy – Game Review: Archon (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lee, Catherine – Companions of Xanth (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Liao, Erick – Ogre Battle Review (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Lo, Vincent – Resident Evil: A Survival Horror Game from Capcom (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Low, Gek Siong – Review of Final Fantasy IV (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Lucas, Christopher – Sonig the Hedgehog (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Mancuso, Jeffrey – Review of TEMCO Super Bowl (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - McCune, Douglas – Captain Skyhawk (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Meza, Gabriel – Warcraft II: Tides of Darkness – Success of Real-Time Strategy Multi-Player Game Online (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Montgomery, Chris – Super Mario Brothers (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Movius, Brennan – Joining the Evil Galactic Empire – A Review of Star Wars: Tie Fighter (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Nguyen, Huy - Zaxxon (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Nycum, Becca – Have you been Trasized (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Ong, Alicia – Game Review of Roberta Williams' Phantasmagoria (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Palmer, Brian – Game Review: Sid Meier's Civilization (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Patnode, Rene – Who Needs Marion? (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Perkins, Andy – Game Review: Full Throttle (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Perry, Todd – Review of Dragon Warrior (The Original) for NES (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Schaeffer, Geoff – Mega Man 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Shen, Walter – Chrono Trigger (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Staley, Storm – The Annelid Menace (The Worms Attack) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Stephenson, Scott – Zork: The Great Underground Empire (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Sylvis, Sean – Game Review: Wolfenstein 3D – Influencing a New Genre (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Tan, Richard – Street Fighter II (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Tannaci, John – Goddard in Victorious (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Tejada, Zoiner – Blade Runner (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Tong, Mark – Pole Position (1982) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Tsang, Audrey – Nancy Drew: Message in a Haunted Mansion – An Investigation into Girl Games (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Waddell, Matt – The Legend of Zelda: Where it all began (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Spring 2001 Assignment 2 Case Histories:
    - Barrett, Ryan – Interactive Music in Computer and Video Games (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Brown, Todd – Why in the World in Carmen Sandiego a Success? (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Chan, Eric – The Driving Technology Behind Quake III: Arena (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chang, Michael – Half-Life Everywhere! (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Chao, Clifford – Case History: Final Fantasy Series (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Chopra, Nitin – Super Mario Bros. Heritage (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Dorie, Tony – LucasArts and Lucasfilm: A Good Deal for All Involved (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Driscol, Adam – Myth: The Beaten Path Less Traveled by Bungie (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Fang, Nicholas – Battlecruiser: When Good Intentions Go Bad (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Hennings, Nathan – Mario Mania: A Case Study of the Mario Culture (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Hu, Yu Ping – Case History: The Star Control Games (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Huang, Po-Wen Joseph – From Populous to Dungeon Keeper: A Tale of God Games (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Jones, Ryan – Quake: 3D is Just the Beginning (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Kochenderfer, Mykel – Jones in the Fast Lane – A Case History in Computer Game Design (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Kuo, Andy – A (very) brief history of cheating [Cheating in Diablo and Diablo II] (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Lee, Catherine – Tomb Raider (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Lee, Jared – The Dune Series (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lo, Vincent – The Rise and Fall of Street Fighter II (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Low, Gek – Coming to American: The making of Final Fantasy VII and how Squaresoft conquered the RPG market (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lynskey, Chris – Leisure Suit Larry (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Mancuso, Stephen – Case Study of Westwood Studios (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Ong, Alicia – The Religions behind Final Fantasy (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Ory, Jeb – KOEI's Romance of the Three Kingdoms: A Titan in Japan, A Tit-Mouse in the US (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Patnode, Rene – Id as Super-Ego: the Creation of Duke Nukem 3D (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Samberg, Joshua – Case History: Pac Man (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Shen, Walter – Pokemon: The Games Behind the Phenomenon and Phenomenon Behind the Games (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Stephenson, Scott – Civilization: Sid Meier's Legacy (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Sylvis, Sean – Case History: Historical Perspective on the Legend of Zelda (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Tannaci, John – Mortal Kombat: Flawless Victory? (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Tejada, Zoiner – The History of Tex Murphy (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Tong, Mark – Side Scrollers: A Planar Odyssey (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Tsang, Audrey – A True Revolution: Case History of the Design of Dance Dance Revolution (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Waddell, Matt – Case History: Where in the World is Carmen Sandiego? "A Mystery Exploration Game" (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Winter 2002 Assignment Case Histories:
    - Winter 2002 Game Paper Archives [incorrectly labeled "Spring"] (1 CD-rom) (Box 3)
    - Acholonu, Ogochi – Oregon Trail and the Evolution of Educational Games (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Adam, Stephane – History Has Never Been so Addictive: The Legacy of Sid Meier and the Civilization Series (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Ansari, Nariman – Nintendo's Legacy of Sequel Supremacy: A Case Study of Super Smash Bros. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Chan, Albert – Headshot! An In-Depth Analysis of the Success of Counter-Strike as a Team-Oriented First Person Shooter and Its Effects on Video Game Culture Around the World (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Chang, Jeffrey – The Fantasy is Never Final: A Case Study on Squaresoft's Design, Licensing, Business and Success with the Final Fantasy Franchise (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Chen, Patrick – Shigeru Miyamoto: Game Designer (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Chou, jim – Case History of the King's Quest Series (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Chun, Michelle – Squaresoft: What's Behind the Hype? (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Davis, Galen – Game Noir A Case History of LucasArts' Grim Fandango (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Dious, Kevin – Why John madden Football Hs Been Such a Success (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Douglas, Aaron – Sound of Music: The Form, Function and History in Video Games (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Douglass, Heather – Adventure Gaming: Where has the Quest Gone? (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Ehrenreich, Ryan – Legend of the Red Dragon (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Fernancez, Rachelle – The Mysterious Laura Croft: Digibimbo vs. Digiheroine (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Guillams, Steven – Online Role-Playing Games: There is Nothing New Under the Sun (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Gunday, Honor – Dope Wars and PDA's The Technophile Drug Dealers Have Finally Found their Platform (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Han, Kang Hyun – Case History Prospectus: The Secret of Monkey Island and Monkey Island 2: LeChuck's Revenge (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hao, Eilene – Metal Gear Solid: An Example of What Game Design Should Be (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Hensley, Ross – Ancient Domains of Mystery and Rougelike Games (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Hwang, Justin – Maximum Convergence (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Ji, Jia – Where Have All the Adventure Games Gone? (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Keh, David – Westwood: The Building of a Legacy (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Kjono, Sandra – The Technological and Business Tactics that Lead to Starcraft's Success (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Kodiak, Michael – drafting a World Understanding the Preeminence of Warcraft in the Real Time Strategy Game (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Koelman, Onno – the Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time-Timely Flagship for the N64 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Lai, Peter – Fallout: Rebirth through Nuclear Holocaust (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Lam, Felix – Aerobiz Supersonic: A Glimpse into the Addictive Business Simulation (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Larson, Peder – Command and Conquer (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Lin, Ruth – Huffin' and Puffin': Can Exercise Games Make the Finish Line? (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Liu, David – A Case History of the Success of Dance Dance Revolution in the United States (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Lopez, Jasmine – Graphics in Adventure Games (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - McCunniff-Reid, Andrew – On the Trail of the Wolf: Wolfenstein 3D Defined the First Person Shooter (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Middleton, Zak – Case History: The Evoltuion of Artifical Intelligence in Computer Games (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Osaki, Harrison – From Diablo to Gate: Differences in Computer RPG Theory (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Park, Andrew – Winning the Game: The Intertwined Histories of Playstation and Final Fantasy VII (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Pop, Andrei – Auteurship and Narrative Modulation in Erick Chahi's Another World (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Pu, Zhichun – There and Back Again: The Story of Subspace (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Ramirez, Mario Luis – Galaga and Vintage Gaming: A Look at Galaga's Place in the Classic Gaming Industry (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Ratan, Rabindra – Simply Smashing (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Risken, Sarah – Pac-Mania: How Pac-Man and Friends Became Pop Culture Icons (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Rozelle, Whalen – Everquest: An Equation for Addiction (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Schuett, Nathan – Activision: A "Recognizable" and "Rewarding" Business Plan (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Segnini, Rodrigo – Music-based Videogames (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Simon, Jay – Zork: A Study of Early Interactive Fiction (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Soon, Yinjie – Case History Star Control III (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Tam, Jeffrey – Intellivision: Its Legacy and the Evolution of Baseball Video Games (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Thomas, Tolu – Case History: The History of Football Games (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Wu, Eddy – Hypersonic: The Meteoric Rise and Fall of Sega (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Wu, Lori – Game and Game Console Emulation: The Preservation of Video Game History (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Wyatt, Zachary – Meridian 69: The Rise and Fall of the First 3D Massively Multiplayer Online RPG (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Winter 2003 Assignment Case Histories:
    - Winter 2003 Game Paper Archives, 1 optical disc (CD-ROM) (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Brownell, Jamie – Case History: The Evolution and Success of College Football Videogames (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Chan, David – The Philosophy of the Sims (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Chew, Andrea – The Adventures of Josie True, A Vehicle for Social Change (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Craig, Miguel – From Dice-Throwing to Interactive Storytelling: The Evolution of the Role-Playing Game Experience (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Daley, Luke – Blizzard Entertainment: A Case History or The Right Way to Make a Computer Game (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Daniels, Roxanne – The Sims and the Need for Fantasy (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Dembo, Adar – Action Movies.. .The Video Game? (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Devkar, Alex – Command and Conquer in the Development of Real-Time Strategy (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Dicker, George – The Future of 3D Graphics Technology: Will the Movies Maintain Their Lead on the Desktop? (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Duffy, Sean – A Perfect Storm: Starcraft as a window into Blizzard's design philosophy and success (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Fang, Jason H. – Of Fighting Games and Fancy Systems: A Look at SNK's Endeavors in the Realm of Gaming (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ferrand, Dianna – Industry Armageddon: Can Heroines Save the Game Industry? (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Flatt, Justin – Myth: The Fallen Lords (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Furtado, Eric – Neverwinter Nights: Bioware Brings the Tabletop to the Desktop (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Hu, Zhong-Min – Bringing the Sony Playstation to Japan: A Case of Business Fitting the Technology (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Jacob, Reza – The History and the Future of Console and Arcade Emulation (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Johnson, Stephanie – Nintendo 64 versus Sony PlayStation: The Cartridge/CD-ROM Battle (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Juarez, Marisa C. – MarioKart in the Hierarchy of Videogames (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Lakkur, Manu – Maxis's Metropolis; the Evolution of the SimCity Series (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Le, Don – Beyond the Violence…A look at the complex world of Counter-Strike (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Lue, Waynn – Video Game Music: Nobuo Uematsu and the Music of Final Fantasy (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Marquez, Matthew – If it's in the game, it's in the game! The Evolution of Madden Football (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Micheletti, Michael – To Err is to Human And Ultima Online… (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Mintz, Nathan – Civilization: Sid Meier's Legacy (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Montgomery, Sean – A Devil in Disarray; How Hacking for Profit Has Crippled the Online Economy of Diablo II (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Nuval, Geoffrey Allen B. – The Plumber and the Hedgehog: A Case Study of Two Games that Defined the Epic Nintendo-Sega Rivalry (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Rayner, Ashley – Beautiful Bounty Hunter: The Story of Samus (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Reeves, Daryl – Sega and the Demise of the Dreamcast (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Shaiman, Todd – The Story of the Sims (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Shedletsky, John – On the Romance of Regicide: The Turk, Kasparov, and Deep Blue (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Shen, Burt – StarCraft: Beyond WarCraft in Space (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Simmons, Keith – EverQuest: Blurring the Lines Between Reality and Fantasy (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Wallace, Kevin – Case History: Sim Basketball (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Warren, Cameron – LucasArts and the Design of Successful Adventure Games: The True Secret of Monkey Island (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Wilson, Douglas – Playgrounds for the Digital Age: Super Mario 64 and the Emerging Identity of Videogames as an Immersive Medium (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Wurman, Oded – To Burn or Not to Burn: That is the Troll Test; An Exploration of Interactive Storytelling in Digital Environments and Neverwinter Nights as its Epitome (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Yu, Janet – Shoot the Moon: Purple Moon and its Influence on Girl Cames (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Zen, Lee-Ming, The Impacts of Medievia and Medthievia (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Zhulin, Vasiliy – Asheron's Call: Redefining the Role of Player Killing (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Zieske, Lawrence – A Case in Study: Tomb Raider (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Zuniga, Eric – Black & White: Fuzzy vs. Finite AI Logic (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Winter 2004 Assignment Case Histories:
    - Winter 2004 Game Paper Archives, 1 optical disc (CD-ROM) (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Balauag, Miguel – Dance Dance Revolution: A True Revolution (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Carbin, Michael – Cultural Transcendance with The Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Chan, Alexander – CPR for the Arcade Culture: A Case History on the Development of the Dance Dance Revolution Community (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Chitty, James – The NBA Live Franchise: An analysis of gameplay and marketing advances over the years since its inception [written with Ben Ilegbodu] (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Christopher, Kevin – Lessons from the Game Cartridge (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Fadia, Ankit – The World of Cricket (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Gustafson, Dave – Pioneering Computer Toys: A New Way to Play (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - DeLaHunt, Jim – Go West, Young Bandicoot: Changes in the Japanese versions of "Crash Bandicoot" for Playstation (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Hurlbutt, Tom – "Regressive" Progression: Non-Photorealistic Rendering Choices in Game Design (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ilegbodu, Ben - The NBA Live Franchise: An analysis of gameplay and marketing advances over the years since its inception [written with James Chitty] (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Kent, David – From Gruden to Belichick: The AI of John Madden Football (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Lee, Kari – EverQuest: Virtual Property Rights (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ong, Qing Yuan – Harry Potter and the Role of Licensed Properties in Video Game Development (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Salinas, Daniel – Sid Meier's Case History: An exploration of the history of narcissistic titles of video games (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Shimano, Kirk – "Floyd Here Now!" A Study of Planetfall's Most Enduring Character (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Shinn, Gini – Case Study: First Generation Pokemon Games for the Nintendo Game Boy (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Stockman, Charlie – The Secret to Miyamoto's Success: An analysis of his early achievements and setbacks (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Tulathimutte, Tony – Toying with the Game: Transgression and Subversion in Everquest (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Wang, Cynthia – The Game Boy's Advance: A look at the staying power of Nintendo's best-selling console (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Restricted files: no release forms or incomplete file
    - Pogue, Zachary – Leisure Suit Larry 6 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Pogue, Zachary – Edutainment – Evaluating the Social Change Value of Carmen Sandiego (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Tan, Richard – Sega: The effects of corporate conflict on game design (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Flannery, Meghan – Golden Eye: The Quest to Re-Invent the Video Game Standard (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mann, Nari – incomplete [form but no paper] (Box 7, Folder 5)